Brian Sturk

bsturk@comcast.net ❖ (603) 809-6825 ❖ Hudson, NH ❖ www.briansturk.com

Seasoned professional bringing over two decades of specialized experience in cybersecurity, threat research, and advanced software development, with a strong focus on cyber threat mitigation and innovative technology solutions.

CERTIFICATIONS & PATENTS

- Offensive Security Certified Professional (OSCP) [Ethical Hacker] License OS-15502
- Patent 11042633 "Methods for Protecting Software Hooks, and Related Computer Security Systems and Apparatus"

PROFESSIONAL DIGITAL ENGAGEMENT

- Presentation at BSides CT Providing Robustness in Endpoint Security Controls (won CTF as 3rr0rsmith)
- Blog Linux <u>CVE-2016-5195 "Dirty Cow"</u> kernel vulnerability
- Blogs Windows "Atombombing", "Macro-less Hacks Retefe Malware"
- Webinar Crypto Crime: Hunting for Cryptocurrency Mining in Your Enterprise
- Ransomware emulation software written in Python
- Extracting Windows PE binaries from png images software written in C++.

WORK EXPERIENCE

VMWare Carbon Black Aug. 2016 – Present

Staff Threat Researcher - Team Lead

Threat Research / Blue Teaming

Remote

- Detection and prevention rules writer for app control, cloud, container, and endpoint products.
- Reversing/detonating malware, threat hunting and emulation for writing and testing product rules.
- Maintained and added new features to Powershell Deobfuscation product using Rust.
- Advanced threat research and cross team collaboration for new product functionality/patents.
- Architect and developer on their next generation rules platform team for EDR and endpoint products.
- Managed VMWare's <u>Microsoft Active Protections Program</u> participation, vulnerability analysis, and Yara rules.
- Various digital engagement activities including blogs, threat bulletins, webinars, and presentations.

Verdasys/Digital Guardian

Jul. 2014 – Aug. 2016

Consulting Engineer - Cyber R&D

C++ Kernel Driver Development / Threat Research

Remote

- Enhanced DLP product's advanced threat detections Process Hollowing, Reflective/App_Init injection.
- New features and support for product's hooking and injection subsystems.
- Coded demos for BlackHat 2014 (iPhone hijacking via malicious image) and 2015 (fileless ransomware).

Avid Technologies

Jan. 2010 - Jul. 2014

Senior Principal Engineer

C/C++ Kernel Driver Development

Burlington, MA

- Development using C/C++ on their ISIS kernel file system driver and related software on OS X and Windows.
- Designed and implemented the embedded Linux platform for the ISIS 2000 product including distribution, installation/upgrade/recovery system, root file system, bootloader, and file system redundancy strategy.
- Designed and implemented a Linux version of the ISIS file system driver using FUSE on RHEL 6.
- Implemented a system for creating, installing, and deploying system recovery images using Qt.

Facilis Technologies

Aug. 2008 - Nov. 2008, Sep. 2009 - Jan. 2010

Consultant

C/C++ Kernel Driver Development

Remote

- Designed and created a new product to allow access to their Terrablock storage product over iSCSI. Heavily
 modified the OSS iSCSI Enterprise Target Linux software package both at the user and kernel level.
- Re-designed and re-implemented their existing file migration application used for movement of files/projects.

- Ported client application to Linux using wxWidgets and consolidated all supported platforms into one codebase.
- Wrote applications to remount and resize Apple Partition Map partitions for OS X.

Jan. 2009 – Jul. 2009 L3 Security

Consultant Woburn, MA Embedded Linux Development

- Wrote diagnostic code for MODBUS based Galil controller over Ethernet doing analog/digital I/O in C.
- Wrote diagnostic code for serial RS-232 based Mforce motion controller in C.
- Implemented Qt based diagnostics interface. Also implemented all QtScript based diagnostic code.
- In house Linux expert for a team of DOS/Windows programmers transitioning into the project.

Tour Andover Controls

Mar. 2006 – Sep. 2006, Dec. 2007 – Aug. 2008

Consultant

Embedded Linux Development

Andover, MA

- Ported 2.6.16 Linux kernel and u-boot to custom ARM AT91 board used for security and automation systems.
- Wrote a Linux kernel driver to handle RS-485 communications utilizing on chip DMA for on board USARTs.
- Implemented use of Debian and Scratchbox/qemu for cross compilation and debugging for ARM9, x86 hosts.
- In house Linux expert to large group of RTOS developers in US and Sweden.

Cylant/Reflex Security

Sep. 2006 – Dec. 2007

Consultant

C/C++ Kernel Driver Development

Lexington, MA

- Ported driver portion of existing Cylant Secure HIDS product to Windows XP from Windows 2000. Driver hooked kernel calls and monitored for rootkits/malware in real time.
- Added features and bug fixes to Reflex Security's Snort based intrusion prevention product on Debian Linux.

JK Enterprises/Kobe Steel

Apr. 2006 – Sep. 2006

Consultant

Consultant

C/C++ Development

Remote

- Wrote an application using wxWindows to interface with a custom data acquisition system over RS-232.
- Removed need for dongle in abandoned application by reverse engineering and binary patching DLL.

Media Matters Dec. 2005 – Apr. 2006

Consultant Python Development Remote

Wrote an application to monitor and interface with a robotic tape archive machine using wxPython.

Siemens SNC LLC Jul. 2004 – Mar. 2006

Embedded Linux Kernel Development Brought up kernel on custom PowerPC 400GX based board on Montavista Linux.

- Ported u-boot bootloader to Siemens' next generation ATCA hardware platform.
- Wrote a Linux kernel driver and API for an MRC FPGA for monitoring board status.
- Wrote a Linux I2C kernel driver to interface with GPIO circuitry, also wrote related diagnostics.
- Wrote a Linux kernel driver and API for Siemens' ARC chip which handled card redundancy/failover.
- Debugged and fixed many kernel bugs in User Mode Linux bundled with the Montavista PRO Linux kernel.

Mar. 2004 – Jun. 2004 EqualLogic Inc.

Consultant Embedded NetBSD Kernel Development Nashua, NH

Billerica, MA

- Coded new features for their iSCSI peer-storage array kernel device drivers on MIPS NetBSD.
- Designed solution and wrote kernel code to detect and fix specific hard drive issues dynamically (*NDA).
- Wrote an application that could induce specific hard drive errors under very high load (*NDA).
- Wrote many applications related to disk drives to monitor, search, diagnose, qualify, and repair them.

Axiam Inc. Nov. 2002 - Mar. 2004

Consultant RTOS / Embedded Linux Development Remote

- Worked on metrology software interfacing with hardware (LVDT, encoders, motors) which ran on QNX.
- Re-designed and implemented their entire system to work with custom ISA data acquisition boards.

Wrote software (neurses application and Linux kernel module) to test their proprietary data acquisition boards.

Pinnacle Systems Apr. 2003 – Mar. 2004

Consultant

C/C++ Windows Development

Lowell, MA

- Added many new features and maintained their VMG broadcast archiving/storage product.
- Implemented an FTP server and client with high performance, multiple threads, 64 bit REST, encryption, and site specific commands for control.
- Designed and wrote an application to query a system's configuration and verify state over a network using Qt.
- Wrote an application to interface with Adrienne time code boards using C# and .NET..

Avid Technologies Apr. 2000 – Mar. 2003

Consultant

C Kernel File System Development

Tewksbury, MA

- Designed, wrote, and maintained Linux kernel file system driver (VFS) and associated device drivers.
- Wrote a kernel file system driver and associated device drivers for Solaris 8.0 (SPARC and x86).
- Wrote kernel device drivers, a file system driver (VFS), and related user-mode tools for Macintosh OS X.
- Wrote an application to interface with Adrienne time code boards using C# and .NET.
- Designed and implemented a reliable protocol over UDP running on multiple platforms and in varying environments, including soft real-time, low memory, and kernel/user mode.
- Designed and wrote a generic, extensible, and distributed testing framework in Python used for smoke testing multiple machines over a network using pyro.
- Implemented redundant server support for products using sockets, INET Helper API, and MFC.
- Reverse engineered the 3Ware IDE RAID/SAN JBOD user mode/kernel mode protocol for integration.

Speedline Technologies/CAMalot

Nov. 1998 – Apr. 2000

Consultant

C/C++ Windows Embedded Development

Haverhill, MA

- Wrote a Win2K kernel driver to access IO boards on parallel ports. Also install and config utilities.
- Implemented many major subsystems for semiconductor dispensing machines including temperature controllers, weight scales, conveyor, digital I/O, motion control.
- Wrote an NT Virtual Device Driver to run DOS based GFX product on Windows NT.

Northern Research and Engineering

Oct. 1997 – Nov. 1998

Consultant

Consultant

C/C++ Windows GUI Development

Woburn, MA

- Provided new features, bug fixes, and an installer for their RITAP product
- Redesigned and rewrote COMIG, their mechanical design software. Also added many new features.

Henschel, Inc.

C/C++ Windows Kernel Development

Newburyport, MA

Jan. 1996 – Oct. 1997

- Wrote NT kernel driver and apps for interfacing/data acquisition with synchro cards and other hardware.
- Wrote many programs interfacing with various military computers/systems using RS-422, NTDS, and Ethernet.

SKILLS & INTERESTS

- **Skills:** C/C++; Python; Assembly language; Cyber security; white hat/ethical hacking; reverse engineering; OS/kernel internals and device drivers; embedded systems; Linux; MacOS; NAS/SAN/Filesystems; RTOS;
- Interests: Capture the Flag/Boot2Roots; Music/Drums; Electronics; Vintage Computers; Boardgames

EDUCATION & MILITARY SERVICE

University of Mass Lowell Electrical Engineering May. 92 - Jun. 1996

• US Army Reserves Rank E4 12C Combat Engineer (demolition, mines). Reclassed to 96B Intel Analyst.